Welcome to Mental Health Monday. We am
sorry for no intro. It's just us, so we
didn't give you any preparation, but
we're so happy that you are here with
us, Dr. White and myself, Atante Meyers.
We're just thrilled to be here with you.
We're back from our summer break. Um,
and we're just again excited to be here.
So, welcome to all of you from all
around the country and the world. And
yes, we are having just a little bit of
technical issues. I know I'm glitchy a
little bit and um I don't know, Dr.
White might be completely in focus to
you guys, but on my end, he looks a
little out of focus, but we decided, you
know what, we're going to go live and
start to share the things that we are
planning to share and take your
questions as a as well because you make
this program uh make it work. So,
welcome, welcome. I almost said Pastor
White. Dr. White.
>> You know, you know what, Dante? I don't
see Clint.
>> I Oh, wow. I don't see Clint. Yeah.
>> Oh, there he is. There he is. Now I see.
All right. That's it.
>> It's like, don't ever. We're sorry.
>> He's not He's not in the number one
spot. That's what I But but we have
Gwendalin in the number one spot. So,
hey, you're holding it down, Gwendalin.
>> Yes.
>> Absolutely.
>> Right. Actually, I see Travis as my
number one. So, I don't know if our
I see Travis Travis H., good to see you.
>> He's my number two. He's my number two.
>> He's your number two. All right. Um All
right.
>> Well, tell us where you're coming from.
Right.
>> Yeah. Please put in the chat. I see
Cindy is saying that she's watching from
Coffee Springs, Alabama. Coffee Springs.
I don't know where Coffee Springs is.
And I'm in Alabama, too. Never heard of
it,
>> but that's great. Coffee Springs. Now,
how was your summer, Sister Tante?
>> Oh, it was great. It was great. I was
just telling um um Ivor a a few weeks
ago that it really was a great summer
because we got to spend time with family
and you know, we got to go to Italy and
different parts of Europe and that was a
lot of fun because where we were, but
also because we were with family.
>> Our mothers were there, our children
were there. It just it was nice. It was
a nice time and
>> other travels too. Just the summer was
nice. And you know what made it the best
summer?
>> It was not that hot here in Alabama. It
really was. And it's like I heard some
locals say that this was the uh coolest
summer that they've seen in like years
or ever really. So I don't know. We had
a pretty mild summer heatwise. So I
don't know what it was like for you in
Southern California, but here in Alabama
we were pretty cool. So how about your
summer? We had a number of days in the
triple digits, which always makes things
uh interesting. But fortunately, it's a
dry heat. Fortunately, it's a dry heat,
so that's so much more tolerable.
>> Um, but uh we didn't we didn't do very
much traveling this summer. Um, we I
remember we did the Euro tour a few
years ago, but we did it like uh in one
of those guided tours.
>> I don't recommend it.
>> Oh my goodness.
>> Okay.
Yeah, I remember I remember being
jealous of like my like meat eatating
counterparts because their dessert
looked delicious. And so I was like,
"Hey man, what about the dessert for the
vegetarians?"
>> The guy brings a styrofoam cup with an
apple in it. And he's like, "Here's your
dessert."
>> I'm like, "Okay."
>> Okay.
>> Wow.
>> It was fun otherwise.
>> Yes. Well, I want to say hi to We have
people. Travis is in Florida. So,
welcome again, Travis. Um, we have Ella
in Australia. Welcome. And Perth,
Australia. Ella, I've never been to
Perth side. I've been to Sydney and
Melbourne and but never Perth. But
welcome. Tell tell me what tell us what
time it is there. Is it It's tomorrow. I
know it's Tuesday, but what time is it?
Uh, and then we have Terry from
Louisiana. Welcome. So good to see all
of you here with us. This is the first
season 4. Season four.
>> This is season four.
>> That's pretty cool.
>> Pretty cool, Dr. White. We're like been
here for a while.
>> Absolutely. And especially when it
doesn't feel like it.
>> No, it doesn't feel like it. It's a lot
of fun. It's a lot of fun.
>> No question.
>> Um, yes. And I want to say welcome to
Shereice from Virginia. Good to see you
here. Good to see you here. But Dr.
White, tell us um about our theme for
this year for season 4.
>> We're so excited and because we want to
be intentional and with it being season
4, we have to uplevel our game. So our
overarching theme is going to be a
growth mindset. A growth mindset. And
all the episodes are going to be one way
or another connect connected to having a
growth mindset. So we estimate that
they're going to be about 18 episodes
and those 18 episodes are going to be
organized around four concepts. Um the
first part of the season we're going to
talk about is vision. Okay, the critical
role of vision. Um you all know that the
proverbs say um where there is no vision
the people you guys could fill it let's
let's see if they'll fill it in the
blanks where there's no vision the
people perish. So the the first part um
we're going to talk about vision. Then
in the second part then we are going to
talking about goals. All right, because
once you get clarified on your vision,
then it's time to
actually set some goals. All right, set,
hey, what is it that we're actually
going to be working for in order to
execute the vision? All right, and so
once you've set your goals, then the
next thing you have to think about then
is execution. All right, no more time.
It's now time to act. it's time to bring
that vision into reality. And so, um,
execution is going to be next. And then
in the last part, we're going to talk
about reflecting.
Um, too often we get so busy in the
process of doing, we don't take the time
to reflect. We don't take the time to
ask ourselves, what did I learn from
this process? Um, what how can I
celebrate this? And then at the same
time also think to myself well how could
I make this even better? How can I
innovate? So reflection is a pivotal
part of um or innovation is a very
important part of reflecting. In fact
reflecting sets the stage so that you
can then innovate. So as you put that
together that will support us developing
a growth mindset. So, did Ella make a
donation?
Is that what that is? $2.99.
>> I
>> I wonder.
>> I know. I was asking for the time.
>> Oh. Oh.
>> Oh.
>> 2.99 is still not a time.
>> That's not a time. I wonder if that's
money. If that's money,
>> you guys all need to follow Ella.
[Laughter]
But anyway, that that is kind of the
overview on how we see this season
unfolding.
>> Um, so yeah, what do you guys think?
What are your thoughts?
>> Yes. Well, hopefully you guys are
looking forward to that, but put in the
chat, what are your thoughts? And um you
know we're going to be talking about
uh today about our emotions and how to
um you know how we can be mindful enough
to get control of our negative emotions.
Um controlling our negative thoughts and
emotions before they turn into something
really really bad. And of course we just
want to mention what the whole world is
talking about. Um, and we're not here to
do a whole program on u the tragedy that
happened last week uh with Charlie uh
Kirk and um all of that. But I mean,
we're here to mention it a little bit,
but not to take a deep dive into that
because that's not what the program is
about. But it's it's really uh it's
really we're focusing more on um how our
negative and toxic thoughts can turn
into bad emotions and then really bad
behaviors like what we saw last week and
it could affect our life forever. Um
because um that's what happened to um
the young man that took uh Charlie's
life and of course it affects his wife
and his children and and so many others.
And so, uh, we know there's a lot of
feelings both ways with this is just a
really, um, just a really, um, horrific
time in Earth's history, right? I mean,
there's always a lot of bad things that
happen and this is not the first
assassination of a, you know, a public
figure and but, um, it's it's still it's
it's just a it's just a sad time. And,
but we know those things are coming.
Those of us who are Bible believing uh
Christians, we know that the world um is
not going to get better before we
believe Jesus is coming back. And so
these things are going to happen.
However, there's things that we can do
for ourselves
um and and controlling working on our
negative thoughts and emotions. And so
uh what are your thoughts, Dr. white.
>> Well, I I I think
with Yeah, I mean I I think with Charlie
Kirk being as young as he was, uh he
was, you know, impacting a lot of
people. Um but especially a lot of young
people, they have some really passionate
feelings about him on either side.
>> Yes. Uh and then now you compound that
with the the graphic nature of the death
and it really leaves the mind in a
really kind of um raw state,
>> lot a lot of emotion, lot of energy,
>> right?
>> And the question before you
and it's the same question you're facing
in every situation that you encounter.
What will you do with the energy?
>> Like Charlie Kirk? What will you do with
the energy? Don't like Charlie Kirk?
What will you do with the energy? Um,
completely frustrated with how the whole
incident unfolded. Um, what will you do
with the energy?
>> Um, will you take time to speak your
truth? Um, and also as you look at the
huge problems this world is facing right
now, what's your contribution to solving
the issue? Because what you see, Sister
Tante, is that energy, it's not just
there to sit there. That energy needs to
be funneled in to doing something
positive, something productive.
>> Um, that really is is the issue. And the
key is to not just be paralyzed.
>> Most definitely. Um and yeah, to do
something good with that energy, the
good thing would be to show love,
to show love in that space. Um and that,
you know, especially to show love, to
show compassion, to show empathy. Um
it's,
you know, it's just to show love and
empathy in that space. You know, I was
talking to someone the other day and I
was like, you know, it's not really
difficult to show empathy to people you
love.
>> But it is challenging at times to show
empathy to people who don't think like
you, look like you, act like you. Um and
so
>> or vote like you.
>> Or vote like you, right? or vote like
you. Um, and so we need to show
more empathy. Um, try to be
understanding.
Um,
and of course you're not going to always
perfectly agree and
um, but not allowing that emotion of
anger, rage to take over.
>> No question. any situation in any
situation. I mean, I like to bring it
home practically.
>> Um because the people that we deal with
the most are
>> are in our home, our spouses, our
children, our other family members, our
co-workers. That's who we deal with the
most. Those are like our our dry runs.
You know what I mean? Those are who we
practice with. Does that make sense?
Like
>> absolutely.
>> Yes.
>> Now, let me see. What about those who
didn't know the person who was murdered
and feel neutral?
What do you think about that, Sister
Tante? What about those who didn't know
the person who was murdered and feel
neutral,
>> right? Um, you know, there's Yeah,
there's no nothing. Yeah, I'm there's
nothing wrong with that. I mean, I'm
sure you don't if you none of us Well,
no, nobody I Well, actually, that's not
true. Do you know somebody who actually
knew Charlie Kirk, believe it or not,
but um it's not about um and that it's
not it's not about knowing knowing him.
Um and I'm sure all of us as humans and
as uh we just of course when someone
someone loses a life no matter
who they are, we should
care. I mean um it doesn't matter the
situation. I mean the fact somebody lost
their life um they were killed we should
care we should you know didn't know him
but um the children lost their father a
a wife lost her husband that we should
have empathy or compassion about that
and even on the flip side for I have as
a mental health professional I mean and
I don't think I have to be a mental
health professional but even for the
young man who allegedly took his life.
Like I have empathy and compassion for
him because in my mind as a mental
health professional I I I don't know
about you Dr. Wright, but I
automatically and I'm sure the same for
you, but I automatically go to what was
going on um in his life. He was
obviously a very broken person in a
situation. And my camera is doing really
weird things. There's like half of me. I
might actually go to You guys can hear
me. You don't have to see me.
>> Loud and clear. Yeah. Loud and clear.
>> Okay. I'm still here. That's better.
Camera's doing weird things.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I was just gonna say that.
>> Go ahead. Yeah.
>> I was just gonna say, you know, thinking
I I have empathy for the young man
because
>> not I mean, of course, he needs if if
when he's found guilty and and and
everything is done correctly, of course,
justice has to be served.
But in my mind, I'm like, man, what went
wrong? like why would you go get to that
point? How did that happen? I mean
that's, you know, that's that's just
where my mind goes to
at 22 years old. I have a 22 year old.
In a week, she'll be 22. And I'm like,
what happens in that short amount of
time?
Well, I mean that really is why we this
is why we do the program that we do
>> because it's our goal to share mental
health principles that hopefully would
be helpful.
>> Um, and you know, it's just a matter of
doing what it is that we can in this
situation. Let's see what Deborah said.
How do the things we look at, the things
we listen to, the people we interact
with cause negative emotions on us?
Please explain
um how that works. You know, it's
interesting. Uh Deborah, uh before
getting on, I was looking for a nice
available
description of stress because if you
look up stress, the definition can be so
laborious and unavailable.
Stress
ultimately is
the resulting experience
from demand.
All right? the resulting experience from
demand. So as you're going through
everything you just mentioned,
>> whether something that you look at,
whether it's something to whether it's
someone you're interacting with, there
are emotions that can result as you
start to feel demand like you've got to
do something.
Now believe it or not there is good
stress which we call ust stress. And so
now if the demand you feel like you have
actually adequate resources for well
that's actually good stress that's good.
But when the demand
leaves you feeling overwhelmed
because your resources are inadequate to
address the demand. That's when we talk
about distress. Distress. So just in
understanding that it equips you to now
start pulling back and assessing
what does this mean to me? What demand
is this placing on me? And therefore
what is the resulting stress that I'm
experiencing?
Is it over in the distress category? And
what do I need to do to pull it back
into the ustress category?
That's why the reality is it's really
important for us to always be tracking
what is it that's within my control.
What can I control and what can I not
control? because it is incredibly
distressing to be trying to control
things that you can't.
And that that is at the hallmark of a
lot of the negative emotions that you're
talking about where sometimes we feel
overpowered or overwhelmed
because sometimes we're trying to
control things that we can't. And by the
way, we are forgoing
dealing with things that are within our
control.
So we are hyperfocused on the the news
media and it's distracting us from
preparing for the presentation that we
have tomorrow for work, let's say, okay,
or for church or for what have you. Um,
now you've missed the opportunity to
prepare for something that was within
your control and and now you have some
self-inflicted distress. So, this is
what you're trying to avoid. Deborah,
does that make sense? Was that helpful
to you? Put a one in the chat if that
was helpful.
>> Yeah, let us know. Let us know.
>> Yeah, that makes that makes a ton of
sense, though.
Yeah. And of course,
>> absolutely.
>> Let's see.
>> Let's see. The point said
the spiritual war we are in is very
real. This should wake us all up to the
seriousness of it all. Okay. Yeah. Okay.
So, yeah. So, Clint was saying, "The
spiritual war we're in is very real.
This should wake us all up." And uh
Charlotte put a one in the chat. Well,
thank you for that, Charlotte.
>> Yeah.
>> Um thank you very much for that.
>> Yeah. So,
>> yes, please put your questions in the
chat because you guys are definitely
part
>> of the program. Um but we were talking
but we also said you know we're going to
talk about um just because obviously
I mean we have none of us know exactly
uh I mean we know that someone is is was
killed and uh we don't know everything
behind the scenes and how it got to that
point. Um but obviously
um
you know someone I mean that the young
man got to the point where he felt like
this is the only the only way and it's
almost like um
his mind was just was taken over by uh
the anger um and the the negative
thoughts and and and and things like
that. And so people
>> any idea what he was angry about?
Well, there's a lot of I don't know for
him. I I don't know. I know this is it's
still unfolding, but um you know,
Charlie Kirk because I see people in the
chat saying, "Well, I didn't know
anything about him." Of course, they
found out when he was passed away, but
you know, he was loved by many, but he
was hated by many or many disagreed with
him. I don't know. I mean, hate hated
hated is hate is a huge a very strong
word. So, you know, it could be any of
the things that he spoke about. He
definitely um spoke about and he was
very open about his thoughts and
feelings u about a lot of things um
dealing with a lot. He was a lot of
things. I mean, deal dealing with black
people here in America, um the LGBTQ
community,
um just a lot of very strong
conservative values that um a lot of con
I shouldn't say a lot that some
conservative people uh believe in, but
was very vocal about it and and he
offended a lot of people. So, I don't
know um what this young man's issue was
and really not to highlight those
issues. That's not the point of this
program.
>> Really,
>> we want to talk about when somebody
doesn't agree with you, when somebody uh
doesn't see things uh the way you see
them. Um or even you feel, you know, you
you know how they make you upset, they
make you you you're passionate about,
you know, whatever. How do you turn that
into something healthy instead of
something negative that can take over
you and cause you to do something that
you're going to regret?
>> Well, I I think it's critical
to
recognize that
our life
if assuming we're Christians,
>> then then our life is not our own.
And the Christian lives under the
mandate take up your cross and follow
me.
>> Not take up, you know, something
pleasant. It's take up your cross and
follow me. So in other words, um we
should be followers of Christ. And
we should commit ourselves to really
tuning into Christ and asking, "Hey, how
would you like me to respond?" Now,
Clint is asking this really interesting
question. He's like, "How do we put
kindness into action as the default
response to situations?"
Now, I think this is where sometimes the
world can really struggle with the
Christian faith or the Christian
theology with a really a
misunderstanding. Are we always called
to be kind?
Um,
hate to be controversial here, but I
don't know that we're always called to
be kind. Sometimes we are called to hold
people accountable. Sometimes we are
called to speak truth to power.
Sometimes we are called to to defend the
weak, you know.
>> Um sometimes to defend the poor. Um and
sometimes holding people accountable is
an act of kindness. So um we we
discipline our children and we don't do
it from a place of hate. We actually do
it from a place of love because we
understand
um the goal is to help you be a
functioning contributing member to
society.
And I think that's more realistic than
the idea that I'm always to be bringing
gifts of sugar plums. Doesn't work that
way. Um so
the but the real question that we're
going to live under is
who told you to do that?
Who told you to do that? Did you tell
yourself to do that or did God tell you
to do that? And the significance there
is as Christians, we're always at risk
of being told of of of saying to Christ,
"Hey, I did this on your behalf. I did
this on your behalf. I did this on your
behalf." And Christ responding, "I never
knew you.
>> I never knew you." No, but I I did all
these wonderful things, but I never knew
you. You didn't tune in to me. We didn't
we didn't have an intimate experience
where I outlined for you how I wanted to
use your life
>> in this grand purpose for the way of
redeeming the world.
>> Right?
>> And I think we we work independently. We
we do what we feel like doing rather
than saying what would God have me do?
What would love really look like in this
situation
as ordained by God as outlined by God?
Clint's got a comeback. Compassion
should always be in our approach though.
Correct.
Um
compassion should always be in our
approach.
Correct. Um, I'm repeating the question.
I think we should always be prepared to
be compassionate. I think the priority
though is follow what God would have us
do. Um, please do not believe I'm
advocating for violence. That is not
what I'm saying right now. But if you
trace the steps of Christ, he does he
does get a little angry in the temple.
And if you if you suspect that he didn't
deviate from God or deviate from his
mission, it's to show you the different
faces of love, the different faces of
love. And you'll only know what that
means if you're tuned in meaningfully to
God. And I'm not talking about those
sweet Christian brothers and sisters
who, you know, the Lord told me
something. No, I'm not talking about
that fake stuff
because we all have been victimized by
people saying that the Lord told them to
do stuff and the Lord did not tell him
to do anything.
>> No, I'm talking about for real for real
when God is ordering your steps. When
God is telling you this is what I would
have you do, it's the David who says,
"Hey, should I go up and do X, Y, or Z?"
Sometimes God says yes and then other
times God is like nah wait till I send
some wind through the mulberry trees or
whatever the tree was. But it it's not
always yes. Sometimes God will have a
different command for you. So um the the
priority is God that God is ordering our
steps. Um then you're good to go,
>> right? And I think what's difficult
for us as humans um is when we are upset
about something that someone said and
again I like to make it as practical as
possible because
the majority of us are not dealing with
um I we mean in the world of politics or
the world of that where people are
saying pay like I'll be honest like I
knew who Charlie Kirk was. I knew I
didn't agree with a lot of things he
said, so I just didn't watch him or
listen to him, right? I just didn't do
it because I can do that. Um, but
there's people who wanted to engage or
listen to everything. So, I'm saying
that typically we're not going to be in
that situation where we're dealing with
somebody on that level, right? But who
we are dealing with is again our spouse,
our significant other, our children, our
our family member, extended family
member. And they will do things and say
things that we don't agree with and we
don't like. How do we respond to them?
And um you know something that I love to
teach and and remind myself as well
because I am absolutely not perfect uh
but is to put ourselves on adult
timeouts, right?
We have to put oursel on an adult
timeout. You you your husband, your wife
says something you don't like, take a
deep breath. And maybe it's more than a
deep breath that you need to take. You
have to literally go put yourself in a
timeout in the corner. It doesn't have
to be in the corner. It could be in the
other room. But what I love to tell
people, but you can't just do that,
especially couples, your spouse, you
can't just walk out and not say
anything. You have to say, you know, I'm
just going to go take a moment for
myself. That is that is the highest
level of maturity.
And that that's hard. That's hard to do.
It's hard to do. But when you take a
deep breath
and actually don't operate just off of
the emotion, but allow this, if you guys
could see me, which you cannot, but I'm
pointing to my forehead, this
preffrontal cortex of my brain, our
brains, if we could just open that up
and operate from there, we're going to
make the right decision. We're going to
say the right thing. We're not going to
just respond uh with the emotion of you
hurt my feelings. Um I don't like what
you said. I'm going to respond in the
most ugliest way that I can. I'm going
to do something, say something, throw
something, god forbid, do anything
physically, something that's going to
harm you. Um but that's what happens
when we don't put ourselves in adult
timeout. Take the deep breath. Go just
have a conversation. And we call it
prayer as Christians, but go have a
conversation with God to help you, to
calm you down, you know, because those
feelings,
those emotions, situations can get us to
do things that um when we don't allow
that to happen that we they can cause us
or we can choose to give in and and it
can cause us to do things that we will
definitely regret.
>> No. Profound. I mean, you should charge
them for that one, sister. That was like
straight psychotherapy 101. Um, the word
I would use is pause. Oh my goodness.
Pause.
>> When you are in crisis, right, when you
are in crisis, the the rule number one
is don't make it worse. Don't make it
worse. And sometimes the very first
thing you're inclined to do
>> is the wrong thing is what's going to
make it worse.
>> And so sometimes you do want to try to
buy time. Now there is an exception to
pause. There is an exception. Now what
is that exception? The exception to
pausing is when you've conditioned
yourself to make the right thing
reflexive.
That's when you don't have to pause.
like when like and and this is what this
is what you see
um elite athletes doing in training.
They are training such that their
reflexes are now conditioned to be the
absolute correct thing in the moment to
where their coaches talk about I don't
want you thinking.
Your muscles now are conditioned to
respond and do the right thing in the
right moment. Your mind is automatically
slowing things down to the point where
you can take advantage of the moment.
So, for example, some of my conditioned
reflexes in the crisis of like if you've
really infuriated me, my response is
actually if you told me something really
provocative,
>> guess what I would say to you? I would
tell you, tell me more about that.
>> Tell me more about that. I think XY blah
blah blah blah blah. Tell me more about
that because I'm actually now buying
time to make sure I heard you right.
See where I'm responding and I am kind
of reveling in the fact that I don't
have to respond right away. I don't have
to respond. I can respond after I've got
clarity on what you're saying because
when the fightor-flight mechanism is
activated,
your IQ goes down.
So what you'll find in these really
volatile arguments, there are so many
misunderstandings.
>> Yeah.
>> So many misunderstandings.
>> Oh, but I thought you said this. No, I
never said that. Oh. Oh, I mean that
that changes everything, you know,
>> and you know why that happens a lot of
times that the the misunderstandings
because we're not really listening.
>> We're listening to respond.
>> We're listening to respond. We're
listening to have a rebuttal and defend
ourselves and not we're not listening
with empathy. We're not listening with
understanding. So when they're like, "I
never said that." Well, and and my the
conversation I had in my head, you said
it, you know, I heard you say that, you
know, and that's what happens when we
don't um
>> Yeah. We don't know how to listen.
>> Absolutely.
>> We know how to we know how to protect
try to protect ourselves, put a wall up
and just defend. We know how to defend
ourselves, but we don't know how to
listen.
>> Absolutely. And then so Deborah said, "A
brother in church told me that
Christians should not live by emotions
but by faith. Do you agree?" This is my
last question. You can you can ask as
many questions as we are here to answer
Deborah. Um
>> correct. Yes.
>> A brethren church told me that Christ
should not live by that Christians
should not live by emotions but by
faith. Do you agree? This is my last
question.
Um, you want to take a first stop,
Sister Tante?
>> Um, all right. Let's see. Now, I'm going
to read it again because I let you read.
>> Oh, I I could I could I don't want to
put you on the spot, but I just Yeah,
>> it's okay. So, I'm not quite sure where
he was coming from, but um you know,
love is an emotion, right? So, we
absolutely ought to operate out of love,
but um of course, we can be I mean, the
Bible says I mean, we're talking about
church, right? So, we're talking about
Christians, so we're talking about the
Bible. Um for those of us who believe in
the Bible, a lot of you are are here
because of you do believe. But um
you know the Bible says to be angry and
sin not. So you can have um righteous
indignation type of anger and um
that so that that's an emotion but you
do the right thing and you do the right
thing in the right way. Like you can be
angry but don't sin. Don't be mean to
someone. Don't cuss somebody out, but
just let them know that this is what
you're gonna do and this is why in a
very kind, beautiful way. I put the
beautiful because just like we say, you
say the beautiful no instead of the ugly
yes. You can have an you can have a an
emotion of anger and respond
beautifully. How about that,
>> man? That was that was gold. That was
gold. She's like, "You might not see my
picture, but I'm dropping science. I'm
I'm I'm coming heavy with it.
>> I gotta do something. They can't see me.
>> They can feel you, though. They can feel
you." Oh my goodness. Um that that was
dope. Um I would say, uh, Deborah, that
I I really I just I like what um I like
what my co-host said. Um I I think that
was really strong. You know, it's
interesting. Whenever we get questions
like this,
I try to go to scripture and say, is
there a scriptural precedence to answer
that question? So now, as I reflect on
the as I reflect on the biblical
stories, I see loads of Christian heroes
using a lot of emotion. Lots of lots of
emotions. um and true sometimes for good
and sometimes for bad. But the point is
it certainly does not condemn the use of
emotions. It's the inappropriate use of
emotions. So when was emotion used in a
good way? You guys remember when the
account that the the people of Jabesh
Gilead
were in need of rescuing and and and
that story came to Saul after he'd been
anointed king and he was flooded with
emotion. He was flooded with emotion and
he and he chopped up some cattle and he
sent it throughout Israel and said,
"This is what will happen to anyone's
cattle who does not come out with us to
help us rescue the people of Jabesh
Gilead." And you'll recall when his body
was desecrated, it was the men of Jabesh
Gilead who went and retrieved his
carcass so that it could be buried with
some some honor. Um, that moment was so
significant.
you of course um when David takes on
Goliath, you see emotion mixed with
faith, you know, uh it's a really
powerful moment because David literally
prophesies, I'm going to chop your head
off. And David doesn't have a sword.
>> So, he must have been foreseeing that
I'm going to use your sword to chop your
head off. But there was a ton of
emotion. So, as I read scripture, I see
quite a bit of emotion
mixed with faith. I will say the more
faith, you know, I I often see the
better the outcome. But I I would be
remiss to demonize emotions or the use
of emotions. We are emotional creatures.
It's just we can't be ruled especially
by negative emotions.
Shereice now said, "What is righteous
indignation versus anger?" What is
righteous indignation versus anger?
>> Good question.
>> You want you want me to go first or
>> is it my turn to go first?
>> I mean,
>> go ahead. I was
>> take a stab at it for what I'm
understanding it to be is I just look at
the example of Jesus. He definitely um
he showed more righteous indignation to
the Pharisees.
And so like he would um respond to them
um and break them down with uh
understanding and logic that they could
not like it basically just kind of shut
them up if you will, but not in a mean
way. Do you see what I'm saying? The way
he dialogued with them was not a mean
way. He just said, well, um, he just
broke it down in in such a way that
they were enlightened with why he was
going and why they were wrong,
basically. So, you can help somebody
understand that they're incorrect or
wrong or what they're doing is not right
without belittling them.
Um, and I think that's righteous
indignation. I mean, and plus, and then
like how what he did when he turned over
the tables. I mean I it I I I I was
timid to use that example only because
>> we don't want oh I can just go I can
just a fool like no and that's not
>> please don't we are also not your mental
health counselors let's talk about
whatever you're hearing confer with your
mental health team before
>> saying don't yeah don't go destroying
furniture in your house I have righteous
indignation
>> well because and and and because now I
mean like let's let's define righteous
indignation like what is the source of
the indignation?
>> What is the source of the fury? Sorry
guys, nine out of 10 times when we
become indignant, it's because there's
been an offense to self.
>> A lot of times when we become indignant,
it's because our pride has been
violated.
That's the difference between us and
Christ. That's the difference between um
like true righteous indignation when
when Christ is turning over the tables.
He is upset
that the sanctuary which was designed to
point people to the plan of salvation is
being adulterated in so vile a fashion.
Like the clinging of the coins is
interrupting the people from even
experiencing the somnity during their
prayer.
>> Right?
>> That's what he's infuriated. The people
cannot even commune with God.
>> Yeah. at the temple.
Like of all places, the one place you
should have an audience and a setting
where you can effectively communicate
with God
is not happening. Now, now Jesus is
upset. That's the kind of stuff that
upsets Jesus. We get upset because
somebody cut us off.
>> Right.
>> We're upset because they gave us the
wrong latte.
>> Yeah. That's not righteous indignation
by
>> that's no that's just that's just
indignation. Um so I think that that's
just anger
>> being rude.
>> That's just anger. You know it's just
you know I'm I'm I'm upset. But in terms
of righteous indignation it's when you
really catch anger on behalf of God. And
here's the other hypocritical thing
about our anger. We get so angry about
the sins
>> we're not committing.
>> Right. Oo, you talking about me? Well,
they can see you in that. They You
dropped that. That was I like that.
>> We get so angry and indignant about the
sins
>> we're not committed.
>> Mercy.
>> We are so impatient
with people who don't have our hangup.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> They have a different hang-up. We get
impatient with people who are not moving
at our
speed of growth and progress. Why can't
you get up to my speed? Dude,
>> you were an Adventist all your life.
>> Like, can you make some allowance for
this other person?
>> Right. Right.
>> And so what if maybe they were schooled
in Adventism as well, but guess what?
They're different than you. You don't
know what their experience was.
>> Right.
that that's not righteous indignation.
>> Just you saying that and I know it kind
of makes it made me go back and circle
back to the Charlie Kirk thing just on
this one thing because people are very
upset on one side and I mean I think you
know on one side they're very upset and
on the other side they're upset but
maybe not as upset as the other side.
But then I'm thinking both sides do when
when you said that it just made me think
like both all people sin. So, you know,
like, yes, you may not like somebody
else's sin. Um, but you shouldn't like
your sin either, right? So, we shouldn't
like it when, you know, Charlie Kirk, of
course, gets assassinated. You shouldn't
rejoice or like that. But like, you
should also be upset when those who
don't agree with you, something happens
because the couple, I think they were in
Minnesota. It was a husband and wife.
They were killed as well. And it it was
a political thing that was, I believe,
earlier this summer or or that type of
thing. You know what I'm saying? Like,
so you you should be upset about
Charlie, but you should be upset when
that when it happens to other people
that maybe don't think like you or not
don't you should be upset period when
this happens.
>> And it's the same thing. I'm just going
along with your whole sin thing. We
shouldn't let our sin,
>> you know, we should not just focus on
other people's sin or you don't like
that, but you shouldn't like your sin
either. I'm just
>> Right. Or or we Well, we we have a
sympathy for our sin, right,
>> but we don't have a sympathy for other
people's sin.
>> Yes. Exactly. Um, it's it's this
inability to get out of ourselves
>> and be present for someone else. Like
>> like that that's what we're
distinguishing like Christ had an
amazing way of getting out of himself.
>> Okay. And and and and getting into the
experience of others.
>> Absolutely. Uh it's it's funny because
the pre uh what would often what would
often precedes Christ miraculous
intervention was a conversation and the
conversation was often what do you want?
>> Remember when he's talking to the blind
man? He's talking to a blind man and
he's still asking what do you want?
>> What do you want? I don't assume that I
know what you want. What do you want?
>> Right? Um, so
>> I kind of want to just take a stab at
Charlotte's um um statement because I
mean it's something I think we should
look at. Like Charlotte's uh Stanford
said, "It seems when Jesus called the
Pharisees
um brood vipers, he he sounds very
emotional
and you know and I and I want us well
this is what I think. I I believe like
we like let's not think in our sinful
minds how we would say that." You know
what I mean? How the like even the body
language or the the you know the our
tone all of that because we know Jesus
was perfect. So okay I got to have that
lens on. How did he say brood vipers?
Did he say it like you know
if I was telling somebody you know the
way you're coming at this is not the
best like you're you know you know the
however he wanted to describe brood
vipers to them. Do you understand what
I'm saying? We we like to we like to
hear it and see it through our sinful
lens how we would say it.
>> We would say it in a mean way if we
don't have God in Christ in us at that
moment.
>> Now what's what's interesting about when
Christ makes that statement, it's not a
random statement.
The creator of vipers is saying you
remind me of vipers.
So, so Christ has an intimate
understanding of what vipers are all
about, what they're like, how they hunt,
how they how they paralyze their their
prey,
>> right?
>> And you're telling me the way the
Pharisees would threaten you with
excommunication
from the community?
>> Yeah.
>> At a moment's notice, remember what they
did to the man that he healed and told
him, "You're out of the community." Do
you understand the the venomous nature
of that? That means where are you going
to get married? And you've been
excavated from the community. Where
where would you allow your child now to
get the rights it needs to be welcomed
into a community? And by the way, what
does it mean when you're pushed out of a
community and you have to now find your
existence somewhere else? It's almost
like a death sentence. It's almost like
capital offense because it's not like
these well industrial nations where you
can be independent and you can be sort
of nuclear and still survive. Your
reliance on community was everything. It
is venomous to kick someone out of the
community. And the ease with which they
did it, I'm sure, is what Christ was
thinking of when he said, "You guys are
like vipers and not just one. You you
plot, you work together. You are a brood
of vipers. And that's being kind
>> when I say what you like. So
he's emotional,
>> cognitive,
spiritual, and still righteously
indignant.
>> Yeah.
and he was Jesus. I guess my biggest um
thing that I want to encourage everyone
and even myself when I read the word is
don't see it through I don't want to see
it through my thoughts and feelings. I
want to see it through God's thoughts
and feelings. And that's why we need to
invite the Holy Spirit every time we
look at those pages.
>> So important for you to say that. My
bias when I'm looking at scripture is
it's loving.
And if it's not,
could it be I'm missing something?
>> And without fail, when I've looked and
searched and thought about it with more
deepness where I didn't see love, now
there was a lot of love. Some of the
some of the places where God looks the
harshest, he's actually being the most
loving.
>> Yes. Yes.
If you make the investment, you will
unearth it.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
I think I mean I'm stealing my husband's
stuff right now, but um the love story,
I think the first time I ever heard
that, it just blew my mind. And that's
that's old. That's like
>> the love story has to be almost 20 years
old, that sermon. That's still
mind-blowing to me.
>> That um Yeah, because we always think
like, oh, hell, fire, the destruction.
That's like that's God's God getting
revenge on the sinner. And it's really
an act of love,
>> mercy. I can still see the the arms of
fire.
>> Yeah.
>> Encircling the the the lost, the wicked.
>> Um that's amazing.
>> Yeah. No, I' I've been so blessed by his
his ministry, man. It's
>> it's something else.
>> Yeah. And I think that's where I mean
that's where the incorrect doctrine of
that hellf fire burns forever and ever
can come because we're thinking in our
own carnal minds like yeah God's going
to burn people forever. Of course they
deserve it. They send you know what I'm
saying like that
>> that it's easy to to go that way. But
the Holy Spirit needs to be invited with
us every time we take a look at the the
scriptures.
>> Amen.
>> Um I think we have time for one last
question. How do you help a child deal
Oh, it went away.
>> Sorry.
>> How do you Okay. How do you help a child
deal with hurt from a par parent in a
positive way? So parent hurt a child
like wow. Yeah.
>> Well, first you get them away from the
parent. I'm just I'm just playing. I'm
just playing.
>> Um you know, as therapists, this is
something I know that you have to deal
with quite a bit
>> all the time.
>> Um what what what say you?
Well, I don't know this exact situation.
Um Um So
>> you need would would it be wise if they
provided you a greater context without
violating privacy? You know, because we
don't want to put any identifiable
information, but just help us to
contextualize a response
>> a little bit better. And I can say
without knowing their situation, just
want to say this while they could be
adding more to that is that I mean I've
just found that unfortunately I was
talking to somebody else and this was
just last week or two weeks ago. It was
outside of the therapy room so it wasn't
a client but I was just sh they were I
think it was over this Charlie Kirk
thing where talking about how much evil
is in the world and I guess I said yes
there is a lot of evil in the world. I
said, but what hap but without most
things don't get it as extreme as
somebody you love gets assassinated,
things like that. However, what does
happen a lot of times is unfortunately
parents aren't being good parents and
not maybe on purpose. They could be not
being good parents because of their own
un um treated childhood traumas and
things that they've gone through. So
they're showing up as parents not being
the best because they didn't have the
best and life has just not been the best
to them and they're just working with
what they have. But unfortunately as
parents we we not on purpose not on
purpose but because of our own not I
should say not all the time on purpose
but we will bring our own brokenness to
the parenting stage and we end up
hurting our children.
>> Yeah. I mean, I I think it was wise to
seek greater context because you get
rotten parents
>> who are damaging their kids. Like
there's a spectrum and you get super
innocent parents and you get parents who
are kind of doing the best that they
can, but they're a little misguided. Um,
and you get, like you just mentioned,
Sister Tante, you get parents who are
being victimized by their past and
they're saying, "Hey, this is how I grew
up." And and you know what's funny? Nine
out of ten times if a parent was exposed
to 10x they're like I'm not gonna be
like that and so they are 8x or 5x and
still and not realizing dude 5x is still
out there.
>> I know you think because I I assure you
the parents that were abusing them were
under the impression that they were
doing a little better than what they
were exposed to.
>> Yeah. Um but so so this this
conversation is on a spectrum and that's
why it can't be given a fair response
without understanding what really is
going on. Is the parent willfully
maliciously hurting a child and then
what intervention is appropriate for
that versus a parent
>> um it's not willful malicious and it's
not even like actually hurting them per
se. And what does hurt mean? Does hurt
mean um offending their feelings? Is it
verbal?
>> Well, they gave a little bit more.
>> Is it? Yeah. Oh, where's their Yeah,
they gave a little bit more context.
They said verbally abusive, threatening
and hitting a child just to see how they
will react.
Yeah, that's
I mean if you're and I again I still
don't know the whole we don't know the
whole thing because we don't know if
this is like the parents are together
and and this is happening in your home
or it's you're separate you're divorced
or whatever and and you share the child
and you he has to go there and you're
not you know what I'm saying? I still
don't know the whole thing, but um
you know if if they are being verbally
abusive and I guess they're threat
threatening to hit the child just to see
how they will react.
>> Um that's abusive. I mean, just to hit a
child and they're
depending on what state you are, like I
are in um I know in California they
physical um punishment
um is can be very shunned by the courts,
but that's a whole another thing. Don't
know where you are. I know. It depends
on what state you are, but um if a child
is in danger, then you definitely have
um resources
um in your in your county, in your in
your state. So, you just uh need to see
if you have to go if you are sharing a
child and you're going to have to go
back to court and let them know this is,
you know, what you've been experiencing
or your child has witnessed and all of
those type of things. And you need to
take it to that level. if you can't um
legally keep them away from a parent
that's being abusive to them. But again,
not knowing all the ins and outs if it's
if if that's a situation where you can
do that. Um if you're living in the home
with them, um that's even probably a
little bit more challenging.
>> Yeah. I mean, there's hotlines, whether
it's,
>> you know,
whether it's 911 or it's 988 or it's
calling the county office to try to
figure out what are the pertinent
resources in your area or it's
connecting with mental health. Um,
there's just a range of appropriate, you
know, responses that it will all depend
on what's the specific thing that you're
dealing with. So,
>> and the original question was how do you
help uh your child deal with the hurt
from so letting them know that you're
especially if you're still with the
parent, you know, letting them know that
you realize that what's happening to
them is wrong and trying to get them
actual help. So, I think professional
help to see a a mental health
professional and that mental health
professional would know more resources
in your area, what to do if you're in a
situation where the county or the
authorities could get involved to assist
you or help you. Um,
>> yeah.
>> So, they would know more. But definitely
you a lot of times um I shouldn't say a
lot of times but there are times when
one parent knows that the child is being
abused but they don't do anything about
it. So even though that parent is not
the abuser or the abuser the child's
going to they end up holding uh res you
know getting feelings of resentment
towards that parent um as well. So
that's why I was saying definitely let
them know that you're here for them and
you are going to do everything in your
power to make sure that they don't have
to continue to experience that.
>> Let's have a let's have a word of prayer
for Shen.
>> Yeah.
>> Um our father and our God. Dear Lord,
you can see um we obviously don't know
the details of this situation, but Lord,
you do. Um we thank you for your
intervention and what it is that you are
planning. And we pray in a special way,
oh God, that um you would intervene
quickly, that you would bring healing,
that you would bring um solace, and that
you would bring a testimony of uh that
would show how awesome and powerful you
are. And we pray this in your holy name.
Amen.
>> Amen. Amen. Well, I want to thank you
for that question. Thank you guys for
all of your questions tonight. Thank
you, Dr. White. Uh, your cra your camera
cleared up beautifully, so you were
good. At least they could hear me. Thank
you, Amra, for being behind the scenes.
Thank you all of all to all of you for
coming and showing up for this season 4.
Want you to know that we will not be
here next week on the 22nd, but we will
be here live on the 29th. So, don't miss
it. put it on your calendar, but also
sign up to get text alerts because
you'll be reminded 20 minutes before we
go live. But we thank you for being here
and please share share this uh share
this program on your social media. I'm
sure some of the answers by God's grace
that we uh answered will be able to
bless others as well. So,
>> Sister Tante, I love how you modeled
resilience.
One way or another, you gonna figure it
out.
>> Yeah, we're gonna figure this out. We're
going to go live. We are here. So,
always a blessing to be here with all of
you and you, Dr. White. And uh we will
see you guys in two weeks. Have a good
>> God bless everyone. Byebye.
>> All right. Bye-bye.